Finding Aid for Program in Conflict Management Alternatives (University of Michigan) records, 1983-1996
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Program in Conflict Management Alternatives (University of Michigan) records 1983-1996
University of Michigan. Program in Conflict Management Alternatives.
9783 Bimu 2
Interdisciplinary program created to study the theory of dispute resolution at the interpersonal, organizational, and societal levels. Records include grant proposals, annual reports, minutes of administrative planning meetings, memos, correspondence, publication drafts, and copies of the organizational newsletter. Also includes minutes, planning memos, reports, audiotapes and transcripts from seminars, conferences and workshops. Contains questionnaires completed by members of grassroots environmental organizations in 1989.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
3.5 linear feet
Transferred by the Program in Conflict Management Alternatives (Donor No. 8503 ) in August, 1996.
No further additions to the records expected.
The record group is open for research.
The Program in Conflict Management Alternatives (PCMA), established in 1985, was an interdisciplinary program at the University of Michigan dedicated to developing the theory of dispute resolution and studying conflict at the interpersonal, organizational and societal levels. In pursuit of these goals, PCMA facilitated communication among core faculty members from different departments and schools at the university, such as sociology, social work, women's studies, and natural resources. Their interest in conflict resolution often coincided with an interest in social justice and social change. The Hewlett Foundation, which supported a string of conflict management centers at American universities (the "Hewlett Consortium"), funded the PCMA from its beginning. The program ended in 1996.
The major venue for communication among core faculty was the seminar, a regular meeting at which an issue or set of readings was discussed. Often, guest speakers were invited to these seminars, brown bags, and colloquia. PCMA also sponsored several conferences at which researchers and practitioners from outside PCMA were invited to attend and contribute. The program also supported courses related to conflict resolution (in cooperation with other departments), publications reflecting research in the field, and a series of working papers which stemmed from the seminars and other activities. Mini-grants and pilot projects allowed the PCMA to allocate funds to faculty members and graduate students conducting research. Occasionally, the PCMA faculty members consulted with organizations, usually non-profits, to help them resolve conflicts and facilitate communication. PCMA faculty also communicated with other researchers and practitioners in the field through the Hewlett Center Consortium. They began to build a practitioner's network to promote communication and continuing education among conflict mediators. Finally, at the University of Michigan, PCMA compiled a manual describing dispute resolution services, and another describing the research interests of faculty members with interests related to conflict theory.
In 1989 and 1990, PCMA, the Institute for Development Research in Massachusetts, and the Highlander Center in Tennessee received a pilot grant from the MacArthur Foundation to sponsor discussions between grassroots activists from America and the Third World. PCMA members also attended several "STP Schools" (the acronym STP is undefined), workshops hosted by the Highlander Center which brought together environmental activists from different parts of the country to share experiences and information.
The PCMA records include grant proposals, annual reports, minutes of administrative planning meetings, memos, correspondence, publication drafts, and copies of the organizational newsletter. Also included are minutes, planning memos, reports, audiotapes and transcripts from seminars, conferences and workshops as well as a set of questionnaires completed by members of grassroots environmental organizations in 1989.
The records are divided into three series: Administrative Files, 1983-1996, Seminars and Conferences, 1986-1993, and STP Schools/MacArthur Project, 1989-1993. Each series in this record group contains audio cassette recordings from various workshops, colloquia, and conferences. For convenience, the tapes have been placed in one central location in the final box of this record group.
Subjects:
Program in Conflict Management Alternatives.; Conflict management.; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); Interpersonal conflict.; Environmental protection--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Administrative Files 1983-1996
  The Administrative Files, 1983-1996, arranged alphabetically by subject, comprise the bulk of the material in this record group. Researchers should note the four proposals and eight annual reports submitted to the Hewlett Foundation, which provide an overview of the program's history and development. The file containing the first Hewlett proposal, in 1985, also contains correspondence among faculty members regarding the decision to found PCMA and seek funding for it. Many of PCMA's ongoing functions are documented in this series. PCMA kept files regarding consultations with non-profit groups, pedagogical efforts (one course and one theme semester), and the publication of two books. Approximately once every year, the program put out a newsletter PCMA News. The working papers put out by the unit are contained within the records of the Center for Research on Social Organizations. Also included are proposals and correspondence related to the distribution of mini-grants, and correspondence regarding Hewlett Consortium activities and events. Evidence of efforts to facilitate communication among practitioners and researchers include the file entitled "Practitioner's Network," and two reports: Planning and Dispute Resolution at the University of Michigan, and Multiple Levels of Conflict: A Guide to Faculty Resources at the University of Michigan. Several folders of administrative minutes, memos and correspondence covering the years from 1985 to 1995 document all aspects of PCMA, especially colloquia and visits by guest speakers. In these memos and minutes, core faculty frequently discuss the state of PCMA and its development. In addition, administrative matters were frequently discussed at faculty seminars. Any gaps in the administrative minutes should be checked against the seminar minutes, within the series Seminars and Conferences.
  - Advisory Board 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
  - Center for Research in Social Organizations (CRSO) Undated (Box 1)
  - Colloquia and Guest Speakers, 7 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - Consultations
    - SOS Crisis Center/Prospect Place (Ypsilanti, MI) 1993, undated (Box 1)
    - Spring Arbor College Consultation and Workshop 1991
      - Planning and Workshop Materials (Box 1)
      - Evaluations (Box 1)
  - Core Faculty
    - Crowfoot, Jim 1987, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Photographs of PCMA Faculty (Box 1)
    - Resumes 1989 (Box 1)
  - Courses
    - Intergroup Relations and Conflict Course 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Theme Semester, Winter 1995 (Box 1)
  - Hewlett Consortium
    - Assessment of Centers for Conflict
      - Correspondence 1994-1995 (Box 1)
      - Final Report 1995 (Box 1)
    - Conferences 1986-1996 (Box 1)
    - Information Exchange 1989 (Box 1)
  - Mini-Grants
    - General (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1988, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Planning Meetings, and Correspondence
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Office Staff 1986-1987, undated (Box 2)
  - PCMA Descriptions 1986 undated (Box 2)
  - Pilot Projects
    - Core Faculty Undated (Box 2)
    - Working Paper on Institutionalization 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Practitioner's Network 1985-1988 (Box 2)
  - Proposals
    - American Council on Education (ACE) 1987 (Box 2)
    - Carnegie Corporation 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - Ford Foundation 1992 (Box 2)
    - Hewlett Foundation
      - 1985
        - Correspondence 1983-1985 (Box 2)
        - Drafts of Final Report (Box 2)
        - Final Report (Box 2)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
      - 1991 (Box 2)
      - 1994 (Box 2)
    - Kellogg Foundation 1986 undated (Box 2)
    - U.S.I.P. 1993 (Box 2)
    - Resource Center for Mediation and Inter-group Relations 1987 undated (Box 2)
  - Publications
    - Announcements (Box 2)
    - Injustice, Social Conflict, and Social Change (Correspondence and Drafts), 1990 undated (Box 2)
    - Multicultural Teaching in the University (Correspondence), 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Multiple Levels of Conflict: A Guide to Faculty Resources at the University of Michigan, 1987 (Box 2)
    - PCMA News, 1986-1993 (Box 2)
    - Planning and Dispute Resolution at the University of Michigan, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Self Evaluation 1986-1987, undated (Box 2)
  - White Faculty Concerned about Racism and Diversity 1987 (Box 2)
- Seminars and Conferences 1986-1993
  The Seminar and Conferences, 1986-1993 series is arranged into two subseries, Seminars, and Conferences and Workshops. Both subseries contain planning documents, minutes, and reports stemming from these events. The Seminars subseries reflects the development of theory in the area of conflict management. The Conferences subseries contains reports and planning materials from several conferences on focused topics, designed to bring together practitioners, and researchers from different disciplines.
  - Seminars 1986-1993
    - Alternative Dispute Resolution 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - Conflict 1988 (Box 2)
    - Empowerment 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Gender 1986 (Box 2)
    - Grass Roots Change 1987 (Box 2)
    - Higher Education 1987 (Box 2)
    - Organizational Conflict 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Social Justice 1986-1989 (Box 2)
    - Seminar Minutes
      - 1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1987 (Box 2)
      - 1988 (Box 2)
      - 1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1990 (Box 2)
      - 1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Conferences and Workshops 1987-1990
    - Alternatives to the Traditional Delivery of Services Undated (Box 3)
    - Changing Racism and Sexism in Organizations 1988
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Proceedings, 8 audiocassettes (Box 4)
    - Conflict in Intimate Relationships (Box 3)
    - Grassroots Organizing Conference
      - General 1988 (Box 3)
      - Conference Summary 1988 (Box 3)
      - Final Report 1990 (Box 3)
    - Hunger and Poverty in the United States Undated (Box 3)
    - Labor Management Relations 1987 (Box 3)
    - Means of Empowerment in Individuals, Organizations and Communities 1989 (Box 3)
    - Multiple Levels of Conflict in Everyday Life 1987 (Box 3)
- STP Schools/MacArthur Project 1989-1993
  The STP/MacArthur Project, 1989-1993 series contains the records created by a collaboration between PCMA, the STP Schools at the Highlander Center in Tennessee, and the Institute for Development Research. PCMA recorded the proceedings of three STP School meetings in 1989, and transcribed two of these. They also distributed questionnaires to the grassroots environmental activists at one of these Schools. These questionnaires are of interest since they describe the tactics, struggles, failures and successes of organizations from all over the country. Another file contains audio recordings of a workshop which brought together activists and researchers from America and the Third World. Other details of this grant-funded project can be found in four folders of correspondence, two proposals to the MacArthur Foundation, and a final report to the Foundation.
  - Costa Rica Venture 1992-1993, undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and Notes 1989-1993, undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Creating International Linkages Among Grassroots Activists (Final Report to MacArthur Foundation), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Evaluation of STP Schools 1990 (Box 3)
  - Highlander Publications 1989 (Box 3)
  - International Environment and Economic Development Workshop 1991, 10 audiocassettes (Box 4)
  - Proposals to MacArthur Foundation
    - 1990 (Box 3)
    - July 1991 (Box 3)
  - STP School Proceedings
    - STP #3 March 1989, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - STP #4 April 1989, 6 audiocassettes (Box 4)
    - STP #11 1989 (Box 3)
    - Two Undated STP Sessions, 2 floppy disks 5.25" (Box 3)
      floppies contain Display Write Word Processing Files
  - Subcontracts 1991 (Box 3)
  - Survey of STP School Participants
    - Completed Questionnaires, circa 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Results 1989 (Box 3)